### James Fish >

# design strategist & facilitator

+49 176 420 64 65 8 james.fish@gmail.com www.james.fish

Designer, facilitator, and music geek, with 10 years of experience helping organizations understand the needs of the people they serve, create better products and services, and build stronger design cultures along the way.

#### Skills 🗲

- Discovery
- Workshop conceptualization & facilitation
- Teambuilding
- Qualitative & quantitative research strategy
- Interviewing, contextual inquiry
- Task analysis, journey mapping
- Visual facilitation & storytelling
- Participatory & co-design methods
- Speculative design & strategic foresight
- Paper & digital prototyping
- Feature roadmapping
- Usability testing
- Market research & analysis
- Miro, Figma, Adobe XD, Sketch
- MS Office and Google Suite
- Adobe Creative SuiteJira, Confluence
- English (native) German C1 Italian C1

#### Education 🕿

## **HPI d.School** / Certificate, Basic and Advanced Tracks

2012 - 2013, Potsdam, Germany Learned human-centric design methods on projects with partner organizations.

#### Harvard University / A.B., Sociology (Economics minor)

2006 - 2010, Cambridge, MA, USA Qualitative/quantitative methods: race and identity, leadership and organizations, healthcare, social entrepreneurship

#### **Professional Experience**

#### **Design Strategy Consultant** (Freelance)

2017 - present (Berlin, Germany)

- Led a 6-month project to redesign a multi-user data analytics tool for intensive care unit clinical teams, identify product and service design issues, and create a mobile UX concept. Conducted dozens of user interviews, facilitated design thinking and speculative design workshops, prototyped and prioritized features alongside product team and senior leadership. ETIOMETRY, INC
- Organized and facilitated a 5-day Google Ventures Design Sprint for a construction tools company. Coached a team of 9 (including senior executives) in design thinking methods. Assessed strategic goals and market needs, prototyped an app concept, recruited and tested with 5 participants. Their experience led them to continue development of the app and hire a full-time innovation manager. CALCULATED INDUSTRIES
- Created and tested a 'masterclass' series of design thinking workshops for HR professionals alongside an HR consulting agency. Facilitated numerous internal vision, mission, and strategy alignment workshops. LISANTIX GMBH

#### Colab Cooperative / Senior Design Strategist



2019 - present (Berlin, Germany)

Colab is a decentralized, transnational tech worker cooperative that serves mission-driven organizations through agile, cooperative digital co-design.

- Led redesign of a web+mobile logistics tool that helps food rescues more efficiently coordinate donations, communicate with volunteers, and see where needs arise across communities. Needfinding, journey mapping, participatory co-design facilitation, wireframing, testing, iteration, feature prioritization, and feedback. The interactive prototype tested well with project partners and volunteers and is currently in development. THE FOOD RESCUE ALLIANCE
- Designed and prototyped an open-source web tool for climate researchers to model carbon emissions and cost projections for various technologies. PROJECT DRAWDOWN
- Designed and prototyped a novel digital media website concept for the relaunch of a social change "storytelling" organization for artists and activists of color. Research, synthesis, conceptualization, wireframing, prototyping features and layout. THE CENTER FOR CULTURAL POWER

#### James Fish

#### design strategist & facilitator

+49 176 420 64 65 8 james.fish@gmail.com www.james.fish

#### Interests >

- Electronic music production, sound design, live performance, DJing
- Music technology: human-computer interfaces, hardware & software instrument design
- Interactive & immersive event production
- Dance (modern, hip hop, flow arts)

#### Elsewhere 2

Design strategy portfolio LinkedIn Soundcloud

**Event production portfolio** 

#### HPI d.School & HPIAcademy / Coach

2017 - 2020 (Potsdam, Germany)



- Guided student teams in design thinking methods and collaboration dynamics on 12-week projects from launch to project partner handover, including two rounds of needfinding, prototyping, and design iteration. Coached teams of professionals in 3-5 day "Intro to Design Thinking" workshops. Mentored participants, gave feedback throughout their projects.
- Created and customized workshops and activities.

#### Proteus Digital Health / UX Researcher



2014 - 2017 (Redwood City, CA, USA)

Responsibilities spanned foundational and generative design research, including needfinding, concept testing, design thinking, and product strategy, synthesizing insights into recommendations for our product team.

- Designed and ran a study evaluating Proteus web portal in clinical workflow context
  - Conducted 14 interviews at 3 customer sites with nurses, doctors, patients, and caregivers, and 11 interviews with naive users in our target market, to evaluate workflows and test feature concepts
  - Synthesized hundreds of insights into 160 user stories, themes, and a feature roadmap
- Co-created a framework for patient health engagement based on peer-reviewed behavioral science
  - Reviewed primary and secondary literature and meta-analyses on behavior change, design, and health
  - Led team in design thinking workshops to ideate features for patient engagement and behavior change
  - Designed an in-app notifications system to motivate users to adopt healthier behaviors
- Coordinated setup at a new customer site, and ran a real-time, longitudinal service design study over 3 months
  - Wrote, programmed, and delivered Qualtrics surveys
  - Assisted with evaluative research and usability studies

**Storia / Product Development Specialist** 

2012 - 2013 (Istanbul, Turkey)

Wellspring Consulting / Associate Consultant 2010 - 2011 (Boston, MA, USA)





